Charles Mingus Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Charles Mingus Collection1939-1979
ML31.M56
Mingus, Charles, 1922-1979
circa 15,000 items 84 boxes 13 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
This is the collected archive of world renowned African American jazz bassist and composer Charles Mingus. The Charles Mingus Collection includes music (manuscript and printed of Mingus and others), writings by and about Mingus by Mingus and others, business papers, printed matter (such as articles and clippings, books and pamphlets, organizations and affiliations, programs, and promotional material), iconography (photographs of Mingus, his family, and colleagues such as Eric Dolphy, Dannie Richmond, Max Roach, Oscar Pettiford, and Miles Davis, artwork, and three dimensional items), personal material, and sound recordings.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Davis, Miles--Portraits.; Dolphy, Eric--Portraits.; Mingus, Charles, 1922-1979--Autographs.; Mingus, Charles, 1922-1979--Portraits.; Mingus, Charles, 1922-1979.; Pettiford, Oscar, 1922-1960--Portraits.; Richmond, Dannie--Portraits.; Roach, Max, 1924-2007--Portraits.
Subjects
Jazz musicians--Portraits.; Jazz.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Purchase; Susan Ungaro Mingus; 1992-1995.
Custodial History
Shortly after the Wolf Trap premiere of Mingus' extended work Epitaph in the summer of 1989, the endeavor to bring the Charles Mingus archives to the Library of Congress Music Division was set in motion. On May 21, 1992, the purchase agreement between the Library and Susan Ungaro Mingus, the musician’s widow, was signed and the first of four deliveries of Mingus material soon followed. Subsequent deliveries of material took place in 1993, 1994, and 1995.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Sound recordings transferred to the Library of Congress, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division.
Access and Restrictions
The Charles Mingus Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Sketch
Date Event
1922 Born April 22 in Nogales, Arizona, to Harriett Sophia Mingus and Charles Mingus, Sr.; Sergeant Charles Mingus, Sr. retired from the U.S. Army on August 31; Mingus family moved to Los Angeles, California; Harriett Mingus died October 3.
1928 Given his first musical instrument, the trombone, by his father for Christmas.
1934 Persuaded by fellow trombonist and friend Britt Woodman, Mingus began studying the cello.
1937 Suggested by high school musician Buddy Collette, Mingus switched from cello to bass.
1938 Mingus introduced to bassist Red Callender by Buddy Collette; Mingus began studying with Callender; began arranging pieces for the high school jazz ensemble.
1939 Began studying composition with Lloyd Reese; composed What Love and Half Mast Inhibitions.
1940 Professional career began at the age of eighteen when he began playing bass with Lee Young.
1941 Began touring with Louis Armstrong's big band.
1942 Played bass with Barney Bigard's ensemble which featured retired trombonist Kid Ory.
1943 Began studying symphonic form and technique with former bassist of the New York Philharmonic, Herman Rheinschagen.
1944 Married Camilla Jeanne Gross on January 3; met saxophonist Eric Dolphy; Charles Mingus III was born on September 12.
1946 Began touring with Lionel Hampton's big band; Eugene Mingus born in September; Mingus separated from wife Jeanne; Mingus takes part-time job at San Francisco post office during Christmas.
1947 Step-brother Odell Carson died in August.
1950 Gained national attention as a member of Red Norvo's trio.
1951 Married Celia Nielson on April 2; moved from the West Coast to New York City for the remainder of his life.
1952 For economic reasons, Mingus for the second time in his life took a job at the Post Office; persuaded to quit that job by Charlie Parker; celebrated his thirtieth birthday recording the first session for his newly formed record label, Debut Records.
1954 Recorded his tunes Getting Together and Gregarian Chant.
1955 Founded the Jazz Workshop, Inc.
1956 Released Pithecanthropus Erectus in September; established Mingus as an innovative jazz composer.
1959 Although Mingus composed the piece at the age of seventeen, he finally recorded Half Mast Inhibitions with a 22 piece orchestra conducted by Gunther Schuller.
1962 With some difficulty, Mingus began search for a publisher for his autobiographical Beneath the Underdog.
1964 Played concert at Monterey; started record company called Charles Mingus Enterprises, which recorded and released the Monterey concert as its first product under the title "Mingus at Monterey"; Mingus elected Jazz Man of the Year by Downbeat Magazine.
1966 Suffering from psychological and financial problems, Mingus began self-imposed exile from public life and performing.
1969 Resumed his music career in June.
1970 Made final music tour of Europe in the fall.
1971 Granted fellowship for composition from the Guggenheim Foundation; a one hour film titled "Mingus" was aired nationally in March and April; Beneath the Underdog was published by Knopf in April; performed at the Newport Jazz Festival in July.
1972 Commissioned to write three-act ballet on "The Life of Malcolm X" for Alvin Ailey's Ballet for the spring of 1972.
1976 Collaborated on album with pop singer Joni Mitchell.
1979 After battling physical complications for several years, Mingus succumbed on January 5.
Scope and Content Note
The Charles Mingus Collection covers the music career of this celebrated African American jazz musician/composer from about 1939, the year he composed What Love and Half Mast Inhibition, to his death on January 5, 1979. Originally estimated to have an item count of less than 10,000, the collection actually contains nearly 15,000 items. The Mingus Collection represents the first multi-format jazz collection processed in the Library of Congress Music Division to include holograph music manuscripts and sound recordings.
The purchase of the Mingus archives by the Library of Congress marks its first acquisition of a jazz composer's written works (both music and literary) and papers. On June 1, 1993, the Library celebrated this momentous occasion with a press conference and lecture conducted by Sue Mingus and Mingus scholar Andrew Homzy. The event culminated on June 4, 1993, with an all-Mingus concert performed by Mingus Dynasty, a jazz orchestra dedicated to the memory and music of Charles Mingus, at the National Academy of Sciences Auditorium.
The Series in the collection include Music, Writings (by and about Mingus), Business Papers, Printed Matter, Iconography, Personal, and Sound Recordings. Each series is rich with Mingus effects and memorabilia depicting his experiences in the world of jazz and some aspects of his private life.
Music Series: Undoubtedly, the central focus of the Mingus Collection is the Music series, the manuscripts in particular. It includes all of his major original compositions as well as his manuscript arrangements of music by others. There are numbers assigned to some pieces - including his adaptations of works by others - but not to all. His original works and his arrangements share one numerical sequence rendering a numerical listing unwieldy, if not confusing. Thus, the music manuscripts are divided into three subseries: Original Music Manuscripts, Mingus Manuscript Arrangements of Music by Others, and Manuscript Music by Others. The Printed Music subseries comprises a small segment of the collection, and is sub-divided into two smaller groupings: Printed Music by Mingus and Printed Music by Others.
Writings Series: This Series is divided into three subseries: Writings By Mingus, Writings About Mingus, and Miscellaneous Writings. The highlight of the Writings By Mingus subseries is Mingus' controversial autobiographical work, Beneath the Underdog, in several versions. Mingus, a proud man, was very much aware of his contributions to the American music landscape in general and to the jazz idiom in particular. This is evident in a one page typescript titled, "A Living Benefit for Mingus". Also included in this subseries are Mingus' manuscript liner notes (written for record album jackets), and articles published in serials.
The Writings About Mingus subseries is principally a collection of articles written about Charles Mingus and his music, some found in serials while others are photocopies of loose clippings. The articles published in serials are divided by publication locale (domestic or foreign) and are arranged alphabetically by article title. The loose clippings, photocopies of the originals, also separated by publication locale, are arranged chronologically by date. This subseries also includes clippings covering particular subjects relating to Mingus and his music. Filed under subject headings, contents here include: articles on Mingus' biography; articles and reviews relating to his literary work Beneath the Underdog; articles on Mingus Dynasty ( the New York- based jazz orchestra established after his death as a tribute to him and his contributions in music); and articles about his widow, Susan Graham Mingus. The Writings About Mingus subseries concludes with a listing of newsletters, press releases, and bulletins relating to Mingus and his music career.
In Miscellaneous Writings are written works on a variety of subjects not necessarily relating to Mingus. The material in this subseries is divided further into three categories: Film Work (Mingus was sought on several occasions to score music for film), Poetry, and Short Stories. The Poetry segment is of particular interest because it contains a work titled Four Poems for Charles Mingus by Lyon Phelps, and a poem written for Mingus’ close friend and colleague Eric Dolphy, titled "Blues for Eric Dolphy," by John Sinclair.
Business Papers Series: Charles Mingus headed three music business ventures: Charles Mingus Enterprises, Inc., Debut Records, and the Jazz Workshop, Inc. Mingus' business acumen and meticulous record-keeping is legendary. An examination of the Business Papers series is a testament to both qualities. Although Mingus did not record dates of his music compositions, it is quite apparent that he realized the importance of documenting everything he considered to be a "business related" matter. He was particularly persnickety about dispensing cash to fellow musicians. He literally used anything that could be written on as a receipt when paying the musicians for services rendered; he had them sign it, regardless of medium: these unique items are included in the collection.
Although there is not a series dedicated solely to correspondence, there is correspondence found throughout the collection. The correspondence in Business Papers, for instance, is quite extensive in that it contains letters to and from three Charles Mingus business entities, and includes names of jazz-world figures such as musicians Sam Most, Max Roach and Dannie Richmond, record producers Teo Macero and Clive Davis, and poet Langston Hughes.
Printed Matter Series: There are six subseries in the Printed Matter series: Articles & Clippings, Books and Pamphlets, Organizations and Affiliations, Programs, Promotional Material, and Miscellaneous. Much of the material in this series does not directly relate to Mingus, but represents his personal collection. The Articles & Clippings and Miscellaneous subseries consist of his personal collection of articles, magazines, newsletters, and press releases not relating to himself. On the other hand, the Organizations and Affiliations, Programs, and Promotional Material subseries do reflect material generated by Mingus' personal and professional life.
Iconography Series: The Mingus Collection contains photographs, artwork, and three dimensional items, filed in the Iconography series. This series is divided into four subseries: Photographs, Awards and Award Nominations, Artwork, and Picture Post Cards. The Photographs subseries contains images of Mingus and his family (including his parents), as well as photographs of fellow musicians such as Eric Dolphy, Dannie Richmond, Max Roach, Oscar Pettiford, and Miles Davis.
Mingus was the recipient of several awards and award nominations, such as the Newport Jazz Festival Hall of Fame Award in July 1976, and the ASCAP-Deems Taylor Award in 1990. In January 1973, Mingus was nominated for a Grammy Award by the National Academy of Recording Arts & Sciences (NARAS).
The Artwork subseries is fairly small, but is very interesting in that it includes record album cover art layouts for Debut Records, some in color. There is one painting by Mingus acquaintance Elliott Cola, who is also represented by music manuscripts (apparently gifts to Mingus) in the Collection, (see Music Manuscripts by Others subseries).
Charles Mingus, among many things, was a traveler. His career as a jazz bassist and businessman afforded him the opportunity to tour the world, his family vacations outside the United States on several occasions notwithstanding. As many travelers do, Mingus collected picture post cards as mementos of his trips. Unmarked and arranged alphabetically by subject, these items are filed in the Picture Postcards subseries of the Iconography series.
Personal Series: The Personal series incorporates Mingus' private archives and an unusual collection of physical effects associated with him. There are six subseries in this series: Correspondence (fairly small compared to the volume of business correspondence), Financial Papers, Legal File, Medical File, Travel, and Miscellaneous.
The Correspondence subseries in the Personal series consists of letters, greeting cards and personal notes from family members, including his sister Grace Mingus, second wife Celia Mingus, and widow Sue Mingus, and friends such as author Helen Gurley Brown, musician Roy Ayers, and comedian/social activist (as well as health advisor to Mingus), Dick Gregory.
The Financial Papers document Mingus’ family assets, banking history, household expenses, and tax records. This material is comprehensive in breadth and gives a fairly clear picture of his personal financial history.
The Legal File includes divorce papers between Charles and Celia Mingus, personal legal correspondence, and documents related to his dealings with the New York City court system.
The Medical File subseries chronicles matters relating to Mingus' health concerns: correspondence from physicians, prescriptions for medications, brochures from health clinics, and statements and receipts for medical services rendered.
As mentioned earlier, Charles Mingus traveled extensively both professionally and privately: the Travel subseries in the Personal series is a record of his personal travels. Following a pattern similar to that of his business dealings, Mingus retained almost everything, especially when finances were involved. The file contains most, if not all, receipts from travel expenses for lodging, meals, and transportation. There is a section in the Travel series dedicated to printed matter acquired while "on the road". It includes maps, travel brochures, and foreign news clippings.
The final section in the Personal series is the Miscellaneous subseries. This contains unusual items that fit no other category of material in the collection. The file includes two calendars of jazz musicians (1973 and 1979), tarot cards, a lock of hair from Eric Mingus' (Charles' son) first haircut, business cards given to Mingus, and a collection of telephone numbers written on a variety of media. One peculiar yet interesting item in this file is a book titled Cultivation of Personal Magnetism in Seven Progressive Steps, by Edmund Shaftesbury, with the mid-section carved out to house Mingus' firearm.
Recorded Sound: Both voice and music recordings are included in this series. The series is sub-divided by format, which includes acetate and vinyl discs (with metal parts), cassettes, and reel-to-reel tapes on five-, seven- and ten-inch reels. The range of subject matter includes voice recordings of interviews with Mingus, Mingus composing at the piano, rehearsals, live performances, studio recordings, and pressed disc recordings.
These recordings are not completely inventoried; most will be transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division (M/B/RS) where they will be prepared for preservation and inclusion in the Library's recorded sound collection.
Lloyd A. Pinchback, February 1998
Organization of the Charles Mingus Collection
The Charles Mingus Collection is organized in 6 series:
Music
Writings
Business Papers
Iconography
Printed Matter
Personal
http://lccn.loc.gov/2004598900
Container List
- Music (Box 1-44)
  The Music series consits of manuscripts of all Mingus' major original compositions as well as his manuscript arrangements of music by others. There are numbers assigned to some pieces - including his adaptations of works by others - but not to all. His original works and his arrangements share one numerical sequence.
  Music series is arranged as follows:
  Music Manuscripts:
  Mingus Original Music Manuscripts, arranged alphabetically by title.
  Manuscripts of Music by Others, arranged alphabetically by title.
  Printed music:
  Printed music by Mingus, arranged alphebeteically by title.
  Printed by others, arranged alphabetically by composer then by title.
  - Manuscript Music (Box 1-29, Box 32-44)
    - Original Music Manuscripts (Box 1-28, Box 32-44)
      - II B.S., Lead sheet; 1 p.; 27.5 cm.; Note: Photocopy of holograph. At bottom: © Jazz Workshop, Inc., November, 1976. (Box-folder 1/1)
      - 12 Alder Place., Full score (incomplete); 4 p. (pp. 6-9 only); 31.5 cm.; Note: Holograph in pencil.; Reference no.: 174. (Box-folder 1/2)
      - 12 Alder Place., Instrumental parts; pagination varies; 31.5 cm.; Note: Holographs in pencil.; Reference no.: 174. (Box-folder 1/3)
      - Abstractions., Lead sheet; 1 p.; 35.5 cm.; Note: Photostat of holograph. At bottom: © December 1976 - Jazz Workshop, Inc. (Box-folder 1/4)
      - Adagio ma non troppo see: Mingus dance no. 7
      - After hours., Lead sheet; 1 p.; 29.5 cm.; Note: Photocopy of holograph. Marked at head: 124. In typescript: Di Charles Mingus - Edizioni Blue Team Music. (Box-folder 1/5)
      - Ain't jivin' blues., Lead sheet; 1 p.; 28 cm.; Note: Photocopy of holograph in pencil. Marked at head: 125. In typescript: Di Charles Mingus - Edizioni Blue Team Music. (Box-folder 1/6)
      - [Alive and living in Dukeland] (#29) / Sy Johnson, arr., Condensed score; [7] leaves; 32 cm.; Note: Photocopy of holograph in pencil.; Reference no.: 001.; Access points: Johnson, Sy (Box-folder 1/7)
      - [Alive and living in Dukeland] (#29) / Sy Johnson, arr., Instrumental parts; pagination varies; 32 and 28 cm. (3 folders).; Note: Copyist's manuscripts in ink and pencil; includes photocopies.; Reference no.: 210.; Access points: Johnson, Sy (Box-folder 1/8-10)
      - Alice in wonderland see: Mingus dance no. 7
      - Alice on wonderland see: Mingus dance no. 7
      - Alice's wonderland see: Mingus dance no. 7
      - All the things you could be right now if Sigmund Freud's wife was your mother., Lead sheet; 1 p.; 35.5 cm.; Note: Photocopy of holograph. At bottom: © Jazz Workshop, November, 1976. (Box-folder 1/11)
      - The arts of Tatum and Freddie Webster., Lead sheet; 1 p.; 28 cm.; Note: Photocopy of copyist's manuscript. At bottom: © December, 1975, Jazz Workshop, Inc.; Reference no.: 002. (Box-folder 1/12)
      - The arts of Art Tatum and Freddie Webster., Full score; 10 leaves; 39.5 cm.; Note: Holograph in pencil.; Reference no.: 158. (Box-folder 32/1)
      - The arts of Tatum and Freddie Webster., Instrumental parts; pagination varies; 31.5 cm. (2 folders).; Note: Copyists' manuscripts in ink and pencil.; Reference no.: 002. (Box-folder 1/13-14)
      - Atomic bomb., Full score; 3 leaves; 31.5 cm.; Note: Holograph in pencil.; Reference no.: 185. (Box-folder 2/1)
      - B.F.T., Full score (incomplete); 2 leaves; various sizes.; Note: Holograph in pencil.; Reference no.: 108. (Box-folder 32/2)
      - B.F.T., Instrumental parts; pagination varies; 31.5 cm.; Note: Copyists' manuscripts in ink and pencil. On verso of bass part: "Portrait".; Reference no.: 108. (Box-folder 2/2)
      - Baby, take a chance with me., Lead sheet; 1 p.; 29.5 cm.; Note: Photocopy of holograph. Marked at head: 126. In typescript: Di Charles Mingus - Edizioni Blue Team Music.; Reference no.: 189. (Box-folder 2/3)
      - Baby, take a chance with me., Full score; 10 leaves; 30.5 x 40.5 cm.; Note: Holograph in pencil.; Reference no.: 189. (Box-folder 32/3)
      - Back a few years (Tijuana table dance)., Condensed score (incomplete); 2 p.; 32 cm.; Note: Holograph in pencil.; Reference no.: 238. (Box-folder 2/4)
      - Back a few years (Tijuana table dance)., Piano part; 2 p.; 32 cm.; Note: Holograph in pnecil.; Reference no.: 238. (Box-folder 2/5)
      - Back home blues., Lead sheet; 1 p.; 27.5 cm.; Note: Photocopy of holograph. At bottom: © November, 1976, Jazz Workshop, Inc. (Box-folder 2/6)
      - Background for thought., Instrumental parts; pagination varies; 31.5 cm.; Note: Copyist's manuscripts in ink. (Box-folder 2/7)
      - Basically speaking., Lead sheet; 1 p.; 28 cm.; Note: Photocopy of holograph. Marked at head: 132. In typescript: Di Charles Mingus - Edizioni Blue Team Music. (Box-folder 2/8)
      - Bemoanable lady., Lead sheet; 1 p.; 35.5 cm.; Note: Photocopy of holograph. At bottom: © Jazz Workshop, Inc., November, 1976.; Reference no: 004. (Box-folder 2/9)
      - Bemoanable lady., Instrumental parts, 2nd and 3rd trumpets only; pagination varies; 31.5 cm.; Note: Copyist's manuscript in ink.; Reference no.: 004. (Box-folder 2/10)
      - Better get hit in your soul / Sy Johnson, arr., Piano-vocal score; 6 p.; 31 cm.; Note: Manuscript in pencil and ink by Sy Johnson.; Reference no.: 100.; Access points: Johnson, Sy (Box-folder 2/11)
      - Better get hit in your soul., Full score; 10 p.; 28.5 x 43 cm.; Note: Holograph in pencil. One page missing.; Reference no.: 124. (Box-folder 32/4)
      - Better get hit in your soul., Instrumental parts; pagination varies; 32 cm.; Note: Copyist's manuscripts in ink and pencil. (Box-folder 2/12)
      - [Better get it in your soul]., Full score (incomplete); 1 p. (pp. 17); 28 x 41 cm.; Note: Holograph in pencil. Title at head: Gitt. (Box-folder 32/5)
      - Better get it in your soul (#6)., Instrumental parts; pagination varies; 31.5 cm.; Note: Copyist's manuscripts in ink.; Reference no.: 153. (Box-folder 2/13)
      - Better get it in your soul: old version., Instrumental parts; pagination varies; 32 cm.; Note: Copyist's manuscript in ink with markings in pencil; includes 1 p. photocopy.; Reference no.: 100. (Box-folder 2/14)
      - Better get it in your soul: new version, Jan. 1963., Instrumental parts; pagination varies; 32 cm.; Note: Copyist's manuscripts in ink.; Reference no.: 152. (Box-folder 2/15)
      - Better git it in your soul: Epitaph., Full score; 17 leaves; 28 x 41.5 cm.; Note: Holograph in pencil. Measures 2832-3090. (Box-folder 32/6)
      - Big Jim Whitey's mule., Full score (incomplete); 10 leaves; 39 cm.; Note: Holograph in pencil.; Reference no.: 130. (Box-folder 32/7)